Finding Aid for the Finci and Musafia Families Papers LSC.2431
UCLA Library Special Collections
Finci and Musafia families papers
1930s-2000
UCLA Library Special Collections
Finci family
Musafia family
Finci, Al
Finci, Rose
LSC.2431
1 linear feet (1 box, 1 half box, 1 flat box)
The collection consists of family photographs and records of the Finci-Musafia family documenting their life in pre-WWII Sarajevo, their experience in the Holocaust in Italy and Switzerland, their emigration to the United States, and their life in Los Angeles.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Al and Rose Finci, 2017.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9919237760006531
Biographical History
Joseph Finci was born December 9, 1895 and Lenka Finci (neé Musafia) was born December 17, 1904, both in Sarajevo. They were members of the Sephardic community in Sarajevo. As Sephardic Jews, they traced their family line back to those who were expelled from the Iberian Peninsula by Spanish royal decree in 1492. Joseph and Lenka married in Sarajevo on January 29, 1928. The following year, Al was born on May 21, 1929. His sister, Erna, was born on January 20, 1934. Descended from a long line of Sephardic rabbis, Al's family was religiously observant.
The Fincis enjoyed life there until World War II. On April 6, 1941, the Nazis and their Italian allies simultaneously invaded Yugoslavia. Within days, they had captured the country. The Germans occupied the northern end of Yugoslavia, and the Italians occupied the Dalmatian coast and some inland areas. Sarajevo was incorporated into the "Independent State of Croatia," a Nazi puppet state under the brutal leadership of the Ustaša. The Germans arrived in Sarajevo on April 15, 1941. They immediately destroyed the Sephardic synagogue in Sarajevo, the largest in the Balkans, and soon began requisitions, expropriations, and arrests. Many Jewish women, children, and elders were interned in military camps while the men were taken for forced labor.
One month after the siege of Sarajevo, the Finci family fled for the Italian-occupied territories. Italian officials often evaded Nazi demands to hand over Jews, transporting them instead to internment camps on the Adriatic islands or to villages in northern Italy, where they placed Al's family. In December 1941, twelve members of Al's extended family disembarked from a coach in Gramignazzo di Sissa, an agricultural village with two hundred residents on the delta of the Taro River. Internment in Gramignazzo meant a state of semi-surveillance with significant restrictions. They were unable to attend school or work, use public transportation or leave the village, plant crops, listen to the radio or read foreign newspapers, or host unauthorized persons. Despite this, they felt safe with the Italians and developed friendships with local townspeople. The children were homeschooled with books provided by DELASEM, and Al's cousins taught him math, world history, and geography.
The Fincis were liberated in September 1943, when the Italians capitulated to the Allied forces. But their freedom was short-lived. The allies won in southern Italy, but were unable to move up through Italy and its territories fast enough to prevent the Germans from taking them from the north. The Fincis went into hiding, and with the help of a clerk in the regional registry and the mayor of Sissa, the family obtained false identity papers to flee the region. In April 1944, the Fincis decided to travel north, deeper into Nazi-occupied Italy and across the Alps to Switzerland. They went through Milan to Moltrasio on the shore of Lake Como, and from there they set off in small groups to cross the Alps by foot in the middle of the night. The Swiss issued the refugees documents, and placed them in schools, foster homes, and hotels empty from the war. Al left his family to go to a Jesuit boarding school, Collegio Maschile Sant'anna, the first time in years that he formally attended school, but was expelled after representing the Jewish students to the principal and objecting to their attending mass. At his second boarding school, he spent his days digging potatoes. Al remained there until the end of the war.
On May 8, 1945, Nazi Germany officially surrendered to the Allies and the Soviet Union, and World War II came to an end in Europe. Al reunited with his parents and sister in Switzerland, and together the Finci family returned to Italy. There they went to Santa Maria di Bagni, the largest displaced persons (DP) camp in southern Italy, housing 2,300 Jews in requisitioned local villas. Two years after the war, the DP camp closed in 1947. Al's family departed for Rome, where they waited for visas to the United States, hoping to join Al's uncle, the only other surviving sibling of his father's 15 brothers and sisters.
In April 1950, the Fincis sailed to New York City with Red Cross passports on the MV Italia, a commercial liner. Once they arrived, the American Joint Distribution Committee provided Al and his family with airplane tickets to Los Angeles to join his uncle. Jewish Family Services helped the Fincis find jobs. His mother did clerical work for the Encyclopedia Americana. His father set up his own export business, sending foodstuffs and other items to Yugoslavia. Al worked odd jobs while at night, he took English classes and exams to earn credits towards a high school diploma.
Within the year, Al received a draft letter from the U.S. army to fight in the Korean War. Al enlisted in March 1951. Once discharged from the army in 1953 with the end of the Korean War, Al enrolled at UCLA with the support of the GI Bill, where he studied accounting. In April 1955, he married Rose Stock, also an émigré from Sarajevo, but from an Ashkenazi family. They had initially met as children in his father's bookstore in Sarajevo, and then again as teenagers in the same Italian DP Camp. When their paths crossed a third time in the United States, they decided to marry. Together they drove to Nevada, where they could marry without the delays caused by the medical tests needed for a marriage license in most states.
In Los Angeles, Rose got a job operating a comptometer, while Al continued his education. Al completed his BA in three years, graduating in 1956 with highest honors and Phi Beta Kappa. While Al continued on to earn his MBA, he and Rose had their first two children, Joe in 1957 and Jeff in 1959. Helen was born three years later in 1962. After graduating, Al joined the accounting firm Seidman & Seidman. He became a partner in 1964 and joined the board of directors in 1969. He retired as Vice Chairman in 1992 from the same firm, later renamed BDO USA, LLP after 36 years of service.
For more information on Al and Rose, see the online exhibit "From Sarajevo to City of Angels: The Remarkable Story of Al and Rose Finci"
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the experiences of the Finci family: Joseph Finci and Lenka Finci (neé Musafia) and their children, Al Finci and Erna Viterbi (neé Finci). The Finci-Musafia families papers consist of materials relating to Al Finci's childhood in prewar Sarajevo; his family's experience in Gramignazzo, Italy and in Switzerland during the war; their time in Rome after; and Al's professional life in Los Angeles. It includes a number of official documents (passports, visas, naturalization certificates, marriage certificates, death certificates, etc.); family photographs; and photocopies of texts about the war.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged both geographically and chronologically.
Related Materials
Sephardic Temple Tifereth Israel Records (LSC.2340). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Sephardim -- California -- Los Angeles; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Finci, Al; Finci, Rose; Finci family -- Archives; Musafia family -- Archives
- Death Announcements for relatives of Al Finci printed in Sarajevo, 1926 January 1-1999 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes announcements for Yosef Finzi (1919), Ašer Leon Finci (d. 1926), Erna Kabiljo (d. 1994), Regina Finci (d. 1974), Ašer Kabiljo (d. 1994), Rahela (Shelly) Kabiljo (d. 1984), and Kalmi Finci (d. 1997).
- Student booklet for Al Finci, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Includes a photograph on the back page.
- School photograph of Al in Sarajevo, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Al is seated in the second row directly in the middle, wearing all white.
- Marriage registration of Al's parents, Jozef Finci and Lenka Musafia in Serbo-Croatian (1965) with an English translation (1966), 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Certificate commemorating Al's first year of school in the Independent State of Croatia, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Reprint of Aser Finci birth certificate, 1939 June 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Reprint of Lenka Musafia's birth registration, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Reprint of Jozef Finci and Lea-Lenka Musafia's marriage certificate with English translation, 1965 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Reprint of Lea Musafia 1903 birth certificate with English translation, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Poem about Sarajevo by Isak Papo, "Sarajevo mi sevdad de oro" (Sarajevo, my city of gold), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photocopy of advertisement for Leon Finci's business in Sarajevo, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Birth Certificate for Josef Finci (b. 12/9/1895) from the Sephardic community of Sarajevo, 1919 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Reprint of Erna Finci's birth certificate, 1940 4 June (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Leatherbound wallet with paper bills, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Erna Finci certificate of Internment, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Minutes of the Municipal Council Meeting conferment of honorary citizenship for Erna and Andrew Viterbi, Rose and Al Finzi, Elaine and Roberto Naiman, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Lenka Finci expresses gratitude to the Italian population, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Al and Josef Finci's bus and tram passes from Rome, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Josef (Giuseppe) Finci (Finzi) business cards from Rome, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Red Cross Passports issued by the delegation in Rome to Josef (1948, 1950), Lenka (1948, 1949), Al (1948, under the name Alexander Finkovic; 1950), 1948 January 1-1950 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Town of Sissa Identity Card for Josef (Giuseppe) Finzi, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Yugoslav Welfare Society in Rome Identity Card for Lenka and Josif (Josef) Finci (Fincovic), 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Finci family lassiapassare, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- International Refugee Organization ID and Travel Authorization for Refugees from Rome to Naples to Detroit for Josef and Lenka Finci and children Al (Aser) and Erna, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Displaced Person Card for Josef, Lenka, and Al (Aser) Finci issued in Como, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- HIAS Identity Card for Al (Aser) Finci issued in Rome, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Italian postal identification card for Josef Finci, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Certificate from Roman Economic bureau for Josef (Giuseppe) Finci (Finzi) and Max Najman, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letter inviting Josef Finci and family to the American Consulate to apply for immigration visas, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Book on the Holocaust in Sissa with a photo of the Finci family on the cover, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Al is pictured on the far right.
- Finci family passport issued by the Royal Legation of Yugoslavia in Switzerland, 1944 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Two maps with key locations circled, one with arrows showing the family's travel route from Como to Moltrasio, Bruzella, Balerna, and Menorisio (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Refugee Cards for Josef Finci (1944-1946) and Lenka Finci (1944-1946) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Al's report card from Collegio Maschile Sant'anna, Switzerland, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes images of the school.
- Photocopies of entry reports from Josef, Lenka, and Erna Finci into made by the Police in Bellinzona, Switzerland, 2006 reproduction of 1944 report (Box 1, Folder 3)
- US passport for Lenka Finci, 1962 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- US passport for Lenka Finci, 1978 August 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- US passport for Joseph Finci, 1962 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Airline tickets to US from American Airlines in envelope and postcard of an airplane, 1950 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Receipt from Gateway Motel in Las Vegas from when Al and Rose got married there, 1955 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Printouts from Museum of the Jewish Diaspora in Tel Aviv about Drohobych, where Rose Finci (Al's wife) was born, Sarajevo, and the name Finci, 1992 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Program for the dedication of the Joseph and Lenka Finci United Jewish Federation Building in San Diego, funded by Erna Viterbi (Al's sister) and her husband Andrew Viterbi, 2001 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Lenka Finci Certificate of Naturalization, 1955 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Joseph Finci Certificate of Naturalization, 1955 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Joseph Finci Death Certificate, 1967 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Lenka Finci Death Certificate, 1994 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Yahrzeit booklet and cemetery information (map, burial location, receipt) for Lenka Finci, 1994 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter from Lenka Finci to the US dept of Justice Immigration and Naturalization Service requesting the Department change her records to indicate her correct birth date of 1903 rather than 1904, 1965 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Telegram alerting Josef Finci of the death of Mark Finci, 1955 August 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter to Al and Rose from a friend who went to Sarajevo and took a picture at a museum of Rabbi Leon Josef Finci, 1990 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Declarations of Intention for Lenka Finci, 1951 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Declarations of Intention for Joseph Finci, 1951 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter from the Shoah Foundation thanking them for their testimony, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter from UCLA to Al thanking him for his pledge to help pay for the Memorial Activities Center at UCLA, 1964 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letter from California Governor, Edmund G. Brown Jr., thanking Al for a meeting at the CA Executive Partners' Workshop, 1981 February 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Profile of Al as a partner at Seidman and Seidman, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Certificate of highest honors in accounting for Al at graduation from UCLA School of Business Administration, 1956 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Al's Los Angeles high school diploma, 1951 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Al's high school transcript from California State Department of Education, 1951 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Business newsletter from Seidman & Seidman featuring Al, 1970 December (Box 1, Folder 5)
- California Society for CPAs newsletters with articles: "Al Finci Chosen as Distinguished Service Award Winner", "Meet your 1978-1979 Committee Chairmen," "Al Finci Named Distinguished Chapter Member", 1978-1991 May (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Program from Al's initiation into Phi Beta Kappa at UCLA, 1956 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Announcement of Al's admission to partnership at Seidman & Seidman, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letter from the Chief Rabbinate Jewish Sephardic Community Sarajevo attesting to the birth of Aser Finci for school registration and showing he knows Serbo-Croatian notarized, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Business advertisements for Kalmus Company printed in California and two of his business cards, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Booklet with the story of "The Family Finzi-Musafia to Gramignazzo of Sissa (Parma)", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- List of the interned people in the Commune of Sissa, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photocopy from unnamed book with mention of Rabbi Juda Josef Finci about the Sarajevo Jewish community, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Booklet "Saved from Oblivion: Oral Heritage of Sephardic Sarajevo", 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Proverbs and Sayings of the Sephardic Jews of Bosnia and Herzogovina, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Program for "Jewish Sarajevo" at UCLA, 2000 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photocopy of text "Jews in the Yugoslav Resistance Movement from 1941-1945", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photocopy of letter Al wrote in the LA times "Jewish Refugees in Switzerland", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Copy of LA Times article "There was nothing Sinister in Swiss Refugee Camps" by Thomas G. Borer", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous photos with captions: Italy, Erna's wedding, Los Angeles, 1944-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Plaque commemorating honorary citizenship to Al and Rose Finci, 2005 November 6 (Box 2)
- Finci family photo album, 1950s-1990s (Box 3)